<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.6.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2017-10-22T16:40:35+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/</id><title type="html">Jonathan Nicholas</title><subtitle>My name is Jonathan Nicholas, and I am a former information security consultant, turned pilot in training. If you wish, you can find out more &lt;a href=&quot;/about/&quot;&gt;About&lt;/a&gt; me.&lt;br&gt;&lt;br&gt; I have created this website because I find that reflecting on experiences is an important way of learning from them.&lt;br&gt; Furthermore, I want this website to be a resource to learn from where anyone else in similar shoes.&lt;br&gt; &lt;br&gt;Please check out my posts on the Blog.&lt;br&gt;  &lt;br&gt;Happy reading!&lt;br&gt;
</subtitle><author><name>Jonathan Nicholas</name><email>notificationinboxio@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">The Wild North</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/flying/2017/the-wild-north.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Wild North" /><published>2017-08-01T00:11:04+01:00</published><updated>2017-08-01T00:11:04+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/flying/2017/the-wild-north</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/flying/2017/the-wild-north.html">&lt;p&gt;I had planned a Commercial Pilots License (CPL) qualifier via Humberside and Sherburn returning to Stapleford. However, weather on the day at the end of May 2017, proved unviable for Sherburn so instead I planned Humberside and Fenland. This trip coincidently had also been the furthest North I have travelled in command of an aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I filmed the route out to Humberside and then the camera battery died just before I landed at Fenland. So instead of ending on a final approach to Fenland, I’ve composed a 2000%-time lapse of my 1hr 35min trip to Humberside totalling 4.5 minutes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;854&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/PQTMvUQtDrg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outbound&lt;/strong&gt; Stapleford (EGSG) -&amp;gt; Potters Bar -&amp;gt; Royston -&amp;gt; Spalding -&amp;gt; Billinghay -&amp;gt; Caistor VRP -&amp;gt;Humberside (EGNJ)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Inbound&lt;/strong&gt; Humberside -&amp;gt; Caistor VRP -&amp;gt; Overhead East Kirkby -&amp;gt; Boston -&amp;gt; Fenland (EGCL)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Return&lt;/strong&gt; Fenland -&amp;gt; Whittlesey -&amp;gt; Royston -&amp;gt; P.bar -&amp;gt; Stapleford (EGSG)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This was the first time I had soloed more than 250nm on my own and exceeded more than 3 hours of flying. CPL Qualifier here I come!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy watching!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[gallery ids=”653,654,655” type=”rectangular”]&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>joncn89</name></author><category term="flying" /><category term="Hour Building" /><summary type="html">I had planned a Commercial Pilots License (CPL) qualifier via Humberside and Sherburn returning to Stapleford. However, weather on the day at the end of May 2017, proved unviable for Sherburn so instead I planned Humberside and Fenland. This trip coincidently had also been the furthest North I have travelled in command of an aircraft.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/cover.jpg" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Compton via the South Coast</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/flying/2017/compton-via-the-south-coast.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Compton via the South Coast" /><published>2017-05-03T21:14:54+01:00</published><updated>2017-05-03T21:14:54+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/flying/2017/compton-via-the-south-coast</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/flying/2017/compton-via-the-south-coast.html">&lt;p&gt;A clear weekend in the UK is a rare event, the weekend in the middle of April 2017 saw high cloud bases (circa 4500ft), relative high pressure and great visibility. On Saturday, I flew to Compton Abbas and on Sunday I flew to Leicester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I filmed the route out to Compton (however, a rookie error surfaced and the camera died on the return):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stapleford (EGSG) -&amp;gt; Tunbridge Wells -&amp;gt; Seaford VOR -&amp;gt; GoodWood/Chichester VOR -&amp;gt; Bishops Waltham -&amp;gt; Southampton Overhead -&amp;gt; Romsey -&amp;gt; Compton Abbas (EGHA)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;854&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/WzMzXy99vKk&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We returned via the Southampton-Bournemouth airspace gap to Cowes, along the south coast and northward to Stapleford.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy watching!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[gallery ids=”625,623,619,618,617” type=”circle”]&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>joncn89</name></author><category term="flying" /><category term="Hour Building" /><summary type="html">A clear weekend in the UK is a rare event, the weekend in the middle of April 2017 saw high cloud bases (circa 4500ft), relative high pressure and great visibility. On Saturday, I flew to Compton Abbas and on Sunday I flew to Leicester.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First Flyout - 2017</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/flying/2017/first-flyout-2017.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First Flyout - 2017" /><published>2017-01-07T14:13:08+00:00</published><updated>2017-01-07T14:13:08+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/flying/2017/first-flyout-2017</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/flying/2017/first-flyout-2017.html">&lt;p&gt;A welcome but unexpected opportunity to fly cropped up on the 02 Jan 2017 when a fellow organiser of the London Flyout meetup group was visiting a friend in Coventry. By luck, a winter high pressure system sat over the UK making for smooth flying conditions and blue skies albeit frosty conditions. This meant we took two Piper Warriors from North East London (North Weald and Stapleford) to Coventry for the day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the past year, I had a lot of history with Coventry (Specifically West Atlantic) but had never actually flown into Coventry. Other Christmas, Santa (my girlfriend) had bought me a Garmin VIRB and this was a prime opportunity to give it a go. So, without further a due, see video highlights of the trip below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;854&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/q1izhoLxLtg&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The precise routing in GBTGY (my aircraft) took:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Outbound&lt;/strong&gt;: Stapleford (EGSG) - Princes Risborough - Westcott NDB - DTY VOR - Draycote Water - Coventry Airport (EGBE).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Return&lt;/strong&gt;: Coventry Airport - DTY VOR - Bedford - Luton Airport Overhead - J8 M1 - Stapleford Airfield.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coventry airport has the Midland Air museum on site and its absolutely fantastic. Your greeted by a hanger full of awesome 40s-80s era aircraft. The outside exhibits however, are the icing on the cake, cold war European, Russian and American aircraft of all uses and sizes. The cherry is the stationed Vulcan where you can sit in the cockpit. An absolute highlight for me, as I had never sat inside one before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A key memorable moment and learning experience was the transition of Luton Airspace returning from Coventry, thinking it was a bank holiday and it would be quiet. Actually it was the counter opposite. There I am furiously scribbling the controller’s instructions, looking for a landing Gulfstream to transit behind and the sun blaring in my face, all whilst the controller tells me: “GBTGY, you’re going to have to be quicker with your responses”. Does that mean I’ve earned my wings after being told off by ATC for being slow?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[gallery ids=”585,584,583,582,581,580,577,578,579” type=”circle”]&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>joncn89</name></author><category term="flying" /><category term="Hour Building" /><summary type="html">A welcome but unexpected opportunity to fly cropped up on the 02 Jan 2017 when a fellow organiser of the London Flyout meetup group was visiting a friend in Coventry. By luck, a winter high pressure system sat over the UK making for smooth flying conditions and blue skies albeit frosty conditions. This meant we took two Piper Warriors from North East London (North Weald and Stapleford) to Coventry for the day.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An Impromptu France trip to Wave Out 2016</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/flying/2016/an-impromptu-france-trip-to-wave-out-2016.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An Impromptu France trip to Wave Out 2016" /><published>2016-12-08T17:19:21+00:00</published><updated>2016-12-08T17:19:21+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/flying/2016/an-impromptu-france-trip-to-wave-out-2016</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/flying/2016/an-impromptu-france-trip-to-wave-out-2016.html">&lt;p&gt;The last likely trip for 2016 was an impromptu one to La Touquet in France on the 04 December. Normally conditions from November to February are pretty poor for VFR pilots. However, a long lasting high pressure system brought on beautiful blue skies in the last and first week of November and December albeit it very cold. Sunday proved to be no exception and was probably one of the best weather days of any that I flew in 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We flew south east from Stapleford to Dover and crossed the channel to Cap Griz Nez at 5000ft before starting a cruise descent at Boulogne to La Touquet. The navigation was a joy as the atmosphere was exceptionally stable and therefore, you could fly hands off once in trim because it was so smooth. Given such a beautiful day it was busy, there was lots of GA traffic the entire way and we could hear London Info talking to GA as far as Carlisle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;La Touquet has a GA commuter reputation and unsurprisingly it was very busy, it took 10mins of travel time before we could get a word in edgeways – Take that Stanstead or Luton control! What was interesting is that we were joining from the north and therefore we were told to join “Early Downwind” by the French controller, not exactly a call I had ever heard before. I was tempted to ask how early but I thought lets not rile the French and make an already tired controller start swearing or as they commonly do, walk off and call a strike!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within 5nm Tower decided to ask us to follow traffic in the circuit instead of “Early downwind” and “positioned us” (which I say in the loosest terms) behind a cirrus on downwind. This involved a 30-degree descending turn whilst ensuring there wasn’t a number 3 or someone behind us. So, a rather interesting circuit join. However, we had the privilege of a lovely sea facing runway and therefore came in on some lovely scenery of the French coast. You can see the landing in the video below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;854&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/J9PiakJCEmQ&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A 25minute walk into town, a stroll by the beach, a crepe and a bimble around Le Touquet town was picturesque albeit very quiet. Accompanied by much the same conditions on the return with the bonus of a setting sun made for a very memorable end of flying calendar 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[gallery ids=”565,564,563,562,561” type=”circle”]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This final trip saw me reach 120hours, with 2016 giving me more memories of tipping my 100 hours on a trip to the Isle of Wight; a conversion onto a Piper Arrow; the start of my IMC and night rating and some success with airline cadetships. Twenty-six memorable hours of flying later I have the desire to do much more, here is to an even more memorable 2017.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>joncn89</name></author><category term="flying" /><category term="Hour Building" /><summary type="html">The last likely trip for 2016 was an impromptu one to La Touquet in France on the 04 December. Normally conditions from November to February are pretty poor for VFR pilots. However, a long lasting high pressure system brought on beautiful blue skies in the last and first week of November and December albeit it very cold. Sunday proved to be no exception and was probably one of the best weather days of any that I flew in 2016.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Aviation History Through Two Airlines</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/flying/2016/aviation-history-through-two-airlines.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Aviation History Through Two Airlines" /><published>2016-10-05T17:48:08+01:00</published><updated>2016-10-05T17:48:08+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/flying/2016/aviation-history-through-two-airlines</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/flying/2016/aviation-history-through-two-airlines.html">&lt;p&gt;The latter half of 2016 saw me see some success with aviation cadetships in two airlines that I follow and I hold in high regard. Both airlines have long standing cadet programmes that intake either PPL standard pilots or candidates with no flying experience. During this time, I did a lot of background preparation and would like to see some of it put to good use so have decided to publicise it here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can imagine these cadetships are highly competitive and selective with single digit intakes where thousands tend to apply. With some luck and hard graft I managed to reach the final stages for both the airlines but unfortunately no further. Whilst this is disappointing, I feel as though I’ve done something right to get to both these stages in one year for two airlines. The two airlines that I am talking about are West Atlantic and Aer Lingus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most, if not all, would have heard of Aer Lingus but West Atlantic possibly not. Both these airlines provide very different services and specialise in different markets. One is a national carrier specialising in passenger transportation with a smaller freight arm (Aer Lingus) and the other is a specialist mail and express logistics freight carrier. At present, both airlines actually have similar sized fleets but comprise of different technologies. I didnt’t want my preperation work to go to waste and thought id illustrate the historical components of my research for both companies using a nice Timeline tool (link below). Both airlines are historically fascinating.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn’t embed the timeline in WordPress. However, I have published them so can be accessed by clicking the airline name (They will look something like the picture below):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cdn.knightlab.com/libs/timeline3/latest/embed/index.html?source=15Ica5QalRG9PPpkpaRoiczpf33EO2MxelhzihaFIios&amp;amp;font=Default&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;initial_zoom=2&amp;amp;height=650&quot;&gt;Aer Lingus&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://cdn.knightlab.com/libs/timeline3/latest/embed/index.html?source=1fXTu67jvOb7Gfmy-kDmZLyJGFf7GmLZL4_6aLyl3FhE&amp;amp;font=Default&amp;amp;lang=en&amp;amp;initial_zoom=2&amp;amp;height=650&quot;&gt;West Atlantic&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2016/10/alvswa.png&quot; alt=&quot;alvswa&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I made the timelines in Timeline js which can be accessed here: https://timeline.knightlab.com/&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Happy History!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>joncn89</name></author><category term="flying" /><category term="Flight and Interview Resources" /><summary type="html">The latter half of 2016 saw me see some success with aviation cadetships in two airlines that I follow and I hold in high regard. Both airlines have long standing cadet programmes that intake either PPL standard pilots or candidates with no flying experience. During this time, I did a lot of background preparation and would like to see some of it put to good use so have decided to publicise it here.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/alvswa.png" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Instrument Flying</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/flying/2016/instrument-flying.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Instrument Flying" /><published>2016-08-22T14:00:48+01:00</published><updated>2016-08-22T14:00:48+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/flying/2016/instrument-flying</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/flying/2016/instrument-flying.html">&lt;p&gt;Since tipping over the 100-hour mark and after encountering awful return conditions on from the Isle of Wight, I thought it would be a good idea to do a rating which would give me the ability to get me out of worsening conditions with confidence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a possible strive for a CPL/IR in the future I thought the Instrument Meteorological Conditions (IMC) would be a good starting point, especially toward earning a competency based IR. Least of all, it would give me valuable skills to confidently navigate variable weather conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After completing the first couple of hours on basic instrument flying going well, my third lesson was on NDB tracking, intercepting and ILS tracking. This was a lesson that made my brain melt! So after this sortie, I thought I’d try and recap what I did by drawing together my thoughts on paper – which are the 2 diagrams below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When my instructor attempted to explain NDB material on the ground we finished the brief in an hour. Three hours later we finish after each one of us becoming confused using practical examples to attempt to solidify understanding! Therefore, I’m not intending on trying to verbally describe it here. Instead, I thought I’d try and draw it in 2 pictures (tracking to and tracking away from) and pray and hope I haven’t confused myself in drawing them up!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2016/08/ndb-tracking-to.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;NDB Tracking to&quot; /&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2016/08/ndb-tracking-from.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;NDB Tracking from&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next is applying these principles to a full NDB hold with wind (diagrams above take no wind into account), which is my next lesson in the air in a new aircraft to me - the PA28R-200 or Arrow. So on top of my brain melting I’m handling a lovely 200hp 120kt aircraft …. How hard can it be?&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>joncn89</name></author><category term="flying" /><category term="PPL Training" /><summary type="html">Since tipping over the 100-hour mark and after encountering awful return conditions on from the Isle of Wight, I thought it would be a good idea to do a rating which would give me the ability to get me out of worsening conditions with confidence.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">One Hundred Hours of Flying</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/flying/2016/one-hundred-hours-of-flying.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="One Hundred Hours of Flying" /><published>2016-04-04T13:30:38+01:00</published><updated>2016-04-04T13:30:38+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/flying/2016/one-hundred-hours-of-flying</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/flying/2016/one-hundred-hours-of-flying.html">&lt;p&gt;Since joining the meetup group “Flyouts from London” in winter last year there have been a select amount of days where the weather has been favourable for a large number of general aviation aircraft to fly to one place. The first was Duxford on a cold clear winter day in February 2016 and the other was yesterday (02/04/2016) for a trip to the Isle of Wight. It was the first day of the year the temperature hit 15 degrees C and there were few clouds in the sky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fly out to the Isle of Wight was the first successful fly out of the year and also the largest – 6 general aviation aircraft from all the local airfields inside and close to the M25 belt: Elstree, Stapleford, Red Hill, Headcorn and Blackbushe. The majority landed at Bembridge (EGHJ) and one at Sandown (EGHN).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My route took me down to the coast via Brighton overhead Shoreham then paralleling the coast to Selsey to then cross over to Bembridge. All of which took me approximately an hour each way. The trip was an important landmark trip for me, as it marked the passing of 100-flying hours total.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[caption id=”attachment_431” align=”aligncenter” width=”650”]&lt;img src=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2016/04/egsg-eghj.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;EGSG-EGHJ&quot; /&gt; Route Out and Inbound[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The outbound trip was fantastically smooth, and surprisingly quiet on all frequencies. The challenge was the Bembridge final approach onto runway 12 left. Although, a very long runway (830m), it is down sloping and the final approach is tight with noise abatement on Brading village. With no published circuit height, my first circuit was done at 1200ft QFE and even side slipping on final on three stages of flap meant I had to go round. My second was done at 800ft QFE and even this ended up me landing a half way down the runway. My takeaway here was to extend the downwind to allow sufficient noise abatement spacing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[caption id=”attachment_437” align=”aligncenter” width=”332”]&lt;img src=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2016/04/img_20160402_101553.jpg?w=680&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_20160402_101553&quot; /&gt; Routing down the Coast[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[caption id=”attachment_438” align=”aligncenter” width=”333”]&lt;img src=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2016/04/img_20160402_103221.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_20160402_103221&quot; /&gt; Bay at St Helens on downwind to land at Bembridge[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A cab across to Sandown, walk by the beach and Sandown pier with a fish and chips in hand for lunch; what more could you want for the first sunny day of 2016? We had a total of 15 people from 6 aircraft meeting up for lunch at a restaurant on the sea front where I wasn’t the only one who had a guilty admission of a go round into Bembridge airport.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[caption id=”attachment_434” align=”aligncenter” width=”536”]&lt;img src=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2016/04/dsc_0879.jpg?w=680&quot; alt=&quot;DSC_0879&quot; /&gt; Beach Party![/caption]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The return trip was the hardest challenge for the day and some of the most challenging flying I have undertaken. Conditions had drastically deteriorated to thick haze and small showers with low level cloud to the east of my return route. Although, conditions were still visual I barely had 7000m visibility and cloud not much higher than 2200ft. I was highly grateful to have a traffic service from Farnborough radar and a GPS receiver for Sky Demon as I gave up my plogged route past Shoreham to opt for a short cut round Gatwick’s CTA to Tonbridge wells and Sevenoaks to then skirt round the London City’s CTA straight into Stapleford for a bad weather circuit. Ultimately, if I didn’t have the GPS, I would have diverted to Shoreham or Goodwood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;[caption id=”attachment_435” align=”aligncenter” width=”545”]&lt;img src=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2016/04/img_20160402_090700.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_20160402_090700&quot; /&gt; The PA28 parked at Bembridge[/caption]&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, a brilliant day, great fly out and learning experience all round. A great way to tip me over the 100-hour mark.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>joncn89</name></author><category term="flying" /><category term="Hour Building" /><summary type="html">Since joining the meetup group “Flyouts from London” in winter last year there have been a select amount of days where the weather has been favourable for a large number of general aviation aircraft to fly to one place. The first was Duxford on a cold clear winter day in February 2016 and the other was yesterday (02/04/2016) for a trip to the Isle of Wight. It was the first day of the year the temperature hit 15 degrees C and there were few clouds in the sky.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Flying Invention</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/flying/2016/a-flying-invention.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Flying Invention" /><published>2016-01-06T13:00:34+00:00</published><updated>2016-01-06T13:00:34+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/flying/2016/a-flying-invention</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/flying/2016/a-flying-invention.html">&lt;p&gt;After a number of navigation trips since passing my PPL, I started looking for efficiency savings in time when it came to flying. I found the biggest use of time is navigation planning in the days before and the morning before the trip. As such, my day job has led me to produce some complex numerical models primarily in Excel and thought I’d try and produce a tool that will automate some of the navigation planning given a set of inputs. All in an effort to let me wake up later on the day!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Navigation planning is exceptionally important and the proper time should be spent on ensuring you have all aspects covered because being unprepared can lead to bad decisions, ultimately making a fun trip, hazardous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have created an Excel “Pre-Flight Calculator” (attached below) which effectively takes a set of variables and calculates: weight and balance (including fuel calculations), centre of gravity (CoG -including aircraft envelopes), and all necessary performance calculations. You cannot automate everything in navigation planning, but after a number of flights using various iterations of this calculator, I have been able to save circa 30-40 minutes on the morning If all pre-flight planning was complete prior.  The model does require input on a number of elements like landing &amp;amp; take-off ground roll and assessment of conditions to establish what performance conditions are pertinent on the day. However, once these are known the results process is automated and near instant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2016/01/pfpm_front.png&quot; alt=&quot;PFPM_front&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2017/07/pre-flight-calculator-v1-9-master.xlsx&quot;&gt;Pre Flight Calculator v1.9 - Master&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have created the model based upon Stapleford Flight Centre aircraft and out of the box it is compatible with the following general aviation aircraft types: Cessna 152 &amp;amp;172, Piper Warrior (PA28) and Arrow (PA28R). However, I have designed this model to be easily adaptable to any aircraft type with foundational excel knowledge given that the user knows the correct information to input i.e. aircraft schedule information, fuel limitations and aircraft envelope details. These can all be seen in ‘Aircraft Schedule info’ tab. What I have mentioned here is aimed at providing accurate weight, fuel and CoG representation. The last part of the model provides automated representation of the performance calculations. This section takes user input variables on airfield and performance conditions and uses model information in the ‘Airfields and Performance’ tab to accurately display required take-off and landing distances.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Audience and Considerations of use:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;I produced the model to streamline my planning. However, I envisage 3 further users for the tool: GA pilots wanting a free and easy to use tool (majority), GA pilots wanting to adapt it (minority) and possibly commercial pilots flying smaller aviation aircraft wanting to adapt it (few).&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to use for general aviation purposes, then you can use this model out of the box with foundational excel knowledge. However, if you want to use it for new aircraft a basic understanding of excel formulae and logic is required to amend correctly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;The model only supports aircraft using AVGAS 100LL fuel with a Specific Gravity of 0.72. It is not compatible with AVTUR because of my current uses. However, the fuel calculations are actually derived using weights and conversions which can be seen in Appendix A tab (AVGAS based). &lt;em&gt;Functionality added in &lt;strong&gt;v1.7&lt;/strong&gt; - See comment #2&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;If you want to use the model with new aircraft types ensure you change the third and fourth yellow tabs (described above) and ensure you sanity check the variables sheet as larger aircraft will require more boxes for more passenger weights and therefore, a small change to the weight and balance tab to reflect the aircraft.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;
    &lt;p&gt;Units in this model are consistent throughout: Pounds [lbs] for weight and Litres [L] for volume. However, conversions to USG and Kilograms [kg] are present in relevant places. *As of &lt;strong&gt;v1.9&lt;/strong&gt;, the introduction of meteorological units (hPa and degrees Centigrade) to ascertain pressure and density altitude in feet have been added - see comment #4.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’d relish feedback on the attached model so please use it, adjust it and disperse it to your heart’s content. Likewise, please feel free to comment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I enjoyed producing this tool as it has given me a better understanding of the aircraft I fly, allowed me to become more efficient in my navigation planning and ultimately I hope it leads me to become a safer pilot.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>joncn89</name></author><category term="flying" /><category term="Flight and Interview Resources" /><summary type="html">After a number of navigation trips since passing my PPL, I started looking for efficiency savings in time when it came to flying. I found the biggest use of time is navigation planning in the days before and the morning before the trip. As such, my day job has led me to produce some complex numerical models primarily in Excel and thought I’d try and produce a tool that will automate some of the navigation planning given a set of inputs. All in an effort to let me wake up later on the day!</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">My First Scottish Munro</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/outdoors/2015/my-first-scottish-munro.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My First Scottish Munro" /><published>2015-10-27T20:59:54+00:00</published><updated>2015-10-27T20:59:54+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/outdoors/2015/my-first-scottish-munro</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/outdoors/2015/my-first-scottish-munro.html">&lt;p&gt;I’d been sowing the seeds with my mountaineering compardre to go and explore a different area of prime British mountains and Scotland was my number one choice. The predominant thing stopping us was finances as 4 days in Scotland were costing us as much as a European package holiday! However, we caught a break when a mutual friend owned a cottage in the Glencoe region of Scotland that he would let us use as long as we promised to take him along.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The weekend trip (23-25/10) was to get us out in unfamiliar territory to practice some ML (Mountain Leader) skills. The weather was predicted to be awful, but luckily they were no were near as bad as predicted. I had arrived on the Thursday evening (22/10) and the cottage was in a fantastic location just off the shores of Loch Leven adjoining Loch Linnhe despite the weary 7 hour journey north from London.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An early start on the 23/10 was to get us out walking by 0830am at the foot of Sgorr Bhan in Ballachullish just on the shore of Loch Leven. The plan was to touch 2 Munro summits, the first Sgorr Bhan (947m) and the second Sgorr Dhearg (1024m). Unfortunately, due to treacherous winds (45mph) and poor visibility due to the tops being in cloud we only did the one Munro and retreated down the way we came.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;23/10&lt;/strong&gt; – Ballachulish - Beinn Bhan - Sgorr Bhan - Beinn Bhan - Ballachulish&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The route began with a steep and gruelling slog up the pathless lower slops overhead Ballachulish with The Pap in the background.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2015/10/img_1475.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2015/10/img_1475.jpg?w=300&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1475&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The first few hours of the day where the hardest because we climbed over 700 metres in less than a single kilometre but this meant we did start to get some pretty spectacular views with Ballachulish Bridge coming into view and the Glencoe Valley later on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2015/10/img_1489.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2015/10/img_1489.jpg?w=300&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1489&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;After climbing up the lower slopes we hit a ridge which uncovered the path which we picked up heading for the ridge line. Once onto the ridge, it is a fine walk on a good path, which soon shows our summit just touching the cloud line with the second higher summit Sgorr Dhearg covered in cloud behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2015/10/img_1488.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2015/10/img_1488.jpg?w=300&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1488&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The weather forecast had warned of gale force winds (up to 45mph) above 800 metres and although we had planned to do 2 Munros, we also planned to retreat if the winds on the summits where too treacherous. Higher up on the ridge line we had already been experiencing 30-35mph winds but we pushed on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2015/10/img_1496.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2015/10/img_1496.jpg?w=300&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1496&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;When we hit the path up to the summit we entered cloud and visibility plummeted as well as winds increasing up to what felt like 40-50mph. The summit of Sgorr Bhan is quite exposed and the three of us had to crouch and scamper over the rocky ridge to the Munro summit cairn which we hid behind for a bit of shelter and recuperation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2015/10/img_1501.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2015/10/img_1501-e1445976449760.jpg?w=225&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1501&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;After 3.5 hours, we had reached the summit of Sgorr Bhan and its here where the three of us decided to retreat back down the way we came due to conditions instead of continuing onto Sgorr Dhearg. 2.5 hours later we returned back to the parking spot in front of the visitor centre in Ballachulish for celebratory coffee and cake of an awesome quality mountain day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A snap from about 700m on the route down:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2015/10/img_1502.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://joncnicholas.files.wordpress.com/2015/10/img_1502.jpg?w=300&quot; alt=&quot;IMG_1502&quot; /&gt; &lt;/a&gt;The size and scale of the Scottish Highlands over shadows my normal stomping ground of the Lake District where most of the Munros are higher than Scafell Pike. As such, I am looking forward to culminating many more Munros in the years to come.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>joncn89</name></author><category term="outdoors" /><category term="Adventure" /><summary type="html">I’d been sowing the seeds with my mountaineering compardre to go and explore a different area of prime British mountains and Scotland was my number one choice. The predominant thing stopping us was finances as 4 days in Scotland were costing us as much as a European package holiday! However, we caught a break when a mutual friend owned a cottage in the Glencoe region of Scotland that he would let us use as long as we promised to take him along.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Montage video of a Flight in a PA28 Warrior</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/flying/2015/highlights-of-a-stapleford-to-shoreham-flight-in-a-pa28-2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Montage video of a Flight in a PA28 Warrior" /><published>2015-10-20T21:06:58+01:00</published><updated>2015-10-20T21:06:58+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/flying/2015/highlights-of-a-stapleford-to-shoreham-flight-in-a-pa28-2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/flying/2015/highlights-of-a-stapleford-to-shoreham-flight-in-a-pa28-2.html">&lt;p&gt;Some memorable parts of a flight I took with a friend to Shoreham (from Stapleford) on the day of the Eastbourne Airshow in August 2015.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;iframe width=&quot;854&quot; height=&quot;480&quot; src=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/embed/197co60dZCs&quot; frameborder=&quot;0&quot; allowfullscreen=&quot;&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A tally-ho moment (just wish i had the RAF tash to back it up):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Waiting to take off at Shoreham at hold point K1 when I get the following radio message from Shoreham Tower:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“GSACO (me), holding at Kilo 1 for the run and break spitfire”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;and quickly followed by the sound of a Merlin V12 roaring past overhead (keep your eyes peeled at about 2mins 20 seconds). This was aptly followed by another call from Shoreham Tower saying:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;“GCO, Line up and wait after the landing spitfire”&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best repeat ive ever had to say!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy!&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>joncn89</name></author><category term="flying" /><category term="Hour Building" /><summary type="html">Some memorable parts of a flight I took with a friend to Shoreham (from Stapleford) on the day of the Eastbourne Airshow in August 2015.</summary></entry></feed>